countries that had butter
страны которые имели масло
and had the opportunity to eat This butter is
а иметь возможность кушать Это масло
not available to all the inhabitants of this
имеют не все жители этой
country, but in the Soviet Union they could buy
страны а в Советском Союзе могли купить
butter.
масло
I heard you correctly that for example
Все я правильно Вас услышал что например
in France not everyone could buy butter. And in the
во Франции не каждый мог купить масло А
Soviet Union everyone could buy
в Советском Союзе каждый мог купить
butter but in line for some reason-  then two packs in
масло но в очереди почему-то две пачки в
hand yes
руки да
Hello Zdra I’m from the city of
Здравствуйте Здра Я из города
Khmelnitsky You’re
Хмельницкий Вы
from the city of Stavropol
откуда город Ставрополь
cool What’s cool Well,
прикольно Что прикольного Ну как
Gorbachev is also a hero Hero of the Soviet
Горбачёв тоже да герой Герой Советского
Union the smartest man
Союза умнейший человек
was
был
Anger Why an
Ангер Почему
antihero I didn’t express my opinion But
антигерой Я высказал своё мнение не А
I’m interested in why he’s an antihero what
вот мне интересно чем он антигерой что
he did
он сделал
wrong  allowed something that should not have been
плохого разрешил то что не нужно было
allowed And that he
разрешать А что он
allowed pluralism And what is pluralism?
разрешил плюрализм А что такое плюрализм
It’s a lot of opinions Yes, yes, that is,
это много мнений Да да а то есть
Gorbachev allowed people to think differently
Горбачёв разрешил людям думать не так
than what the party said, you can think
как сказала партия ты можешь думать Всё
Anything but do You must do what you
что угодно но делать Ты должен то что
need Yeah That is, until  Gorbachev was
нужно Ага То есть до Горбачёва было
allowed to think whatever he wanted, just
разрешено думать что угодно дела только
what the party would say. Yes, I don’t know what
то что скажет партия Да я не знаю что
happened before Gorbachev, wait. So what
было до Горбачёва подожди Так а что
did Gorbachev allow? Well, what does it mean
разрешил Горбачёв Ну что имеется в виду
that pluralism? He allowed the tongue to wag,
что плюрализм Он разрешил языком трепать
you know, I understand how it is, what is this word
понимаешь а Поня как это как это слово
called when a person promises
называется когда человек обещает
in advance?  unrealistic politician like
заведомо нереалистично политик типа
five years per year populism no populism
пятилетку в года популизм нет популизм а
but building Communism is populism or
вот построить Коммунизм это популизм или
not
нет Вот
Well, the whole Soviet Union was moving towards
Ну так весь Советский Союз шл к тому
building communism That is, it
чтобы строить коммунизм То есть
turns out that the Communist Party was engaged in
получается компартия занималась
populism Well, there were some ideologists
популизм Ну были какие-то идеологи
who maybe believed in this, well,
которые может быть в это верили ну
wait a little longer  since the party clearly said
подожди ещё раз партия чётко говорила
that we are building communism Well, yes And you
что мы строим коммунизм Ну да А вы
say Gorbachev allowed pluralism and you
говорите а Горбачёв разрешил плюрализм и
could already say anything you
можно было уже говорить что угодно ти вы
want you want to hear my
хотите вы хотите услышать мою
primitive
примитивное
is when there is some kind of
это когда есть какая-то
ideology, this ideology needs to
идеология это идеологии нужно
feed the people, that is, the ideology was
кормить народ то есть идеология была
offered to the people  instead of religion, that is,
предложена народу вместо религии то есть
people had to believe that in the distant
люди должны были верить что в далёком
future their children, grandchildren, great-grandchildren would
будущем их дети внуки правнуки будут
live like this. Under this system, although it was
жить вот При таком строе Хотя это было
unrealistic logo
нереалистично лого
before Gorbachev, it turns out that Liu ruined the
до Горбачёва получается лю развалил
dream, the dream ruined the people, so people
мечту мечту развалил людей так людей
were deceived, you yourself said that this is
обманывали вы сами сказали что это
Utopia for people to sell utopia and Gorbachev
Утопия людям впаривать утопию а Горбачёв
allowed to talk about other things allowed to
разрешил говорить про другое разрешил
criticize a person is a being
критиковать человек такое существо
who must believe in something,
которое должно во что-то верить верить
he must believe in something in order for
оно должно во что-то для того чтобы у
him to have some kind of
него были какие-то
restraining ardor of nature Yes,
сдерживающие его пыл натуру Да
restraining barriers Yeah, it doesn’t matter that it’s a
сдерживающие барьеры Угу неважно что это
religion,
религия
there’s some kind of military regime  Yes,
там военный какой-то режим Да человека
something must hold a person back, otherwise he
должно что-то сдерживать иначе его
will be blown away in all directions, so I understood, but what, for
разнесёт во все стороны так понял а что
example, holds people back there in
например сдерживает людей там во
France, I don’t know, I haven’t been to France. Well,
Франции я не знаю я не был во Франции Ну
what kind of religion is there? Or what,
какая там есть какая-то религия Или что
what is holding them back like that, or in Spain
что их вот так сдерживает или в Испании
what?  we are Great Democracy Yeah I understand yes
что мы Великая демократия Ага понял да
Everything is European This will hold back yes and
Всё всё европейски Вот это сдержит да а
in Yes in the Soviet Union it turns out there was
в Да в Советском Союзе получается была
Utopia communism Yes but Gorbachev allowed to
Утопия коммунизм Да но Горбачёв разрешил
criticize allowed to say anything
критиковать разрешил говорить что угодно
Yes I just said
Да я же только что сказал
Gorbachev destroyed you know the people's
Горбачёв разрушил понимаешь людскую
dream Hope
мечту Надежду
[music]
[музыка]
Faith in that  that communism will someday be
Веру в то что коммунизм когда-то будет
built That is, I understand correctly that
построен То есть я правильно понимаю что
before Gorbachev people lived in
до Горбачёва люди Вот они жили в
poverty, there were no goods on the
бедности не было там товаров на
shelves Yes, but they believed that one day
прилавках Да но верили что когда-то у
their grandchildren would have this, and it was completely in the
ихних внуков будет это да совершенно в
hole Yes, I understand, and Gorbachev traveled at the same time
дырочку Да Поня а Горбачёв при этом
in other countries as the President and
ездил по другим странам как Президент и
you see that in other countries this already exists.
видиш что в других странах это уже есть
No, this is not available anywhere on the planet.
Нет этого нигде нет на планете з
Wait, there was oil, for example, here is oil.
Подождите масло было например вот масло
For example, here you are. Yes, we are now talking about
Например у нас вы Да мы сейчас говорим о
communism or about oil, well, well, what
коммунизме или о масле а а ну а что что
would
бы означало
communism mean? Read  what is ko not for a
коммунизм Почитай что такое ко не для
person Specifically, what will he have,
человека Конкретно что у него будет
what from each, if possible, To each according to his
что от каждого по возможности Каждому по
needs, how old are you,
потребностям сколько тебе лет вот вот
look, how old are you? Tell me
смотрите вот у ско тебе лет Скажи мне
please, I’m in the first year of
пожалуйста я во первого года
birth. I spent 10 years in the Soviet
рождения Я 10 лет хват нул Советского
Union. Yes, the need for oil, for example.  a
Союза Да потребность в масле например
person has and was in the Soviet
есть у человека и была в Советском
Union Yes, but there was no butter and they
Союзе Да а масла не было и масло
gave two packs of butter to each person’s hands like this. Communism
выдавали две пачки в руки так Коммунизм
is when you have enough butter or when
- это когда тебе хватает масла или когда
you just said something from everyone, if
что ты токо что сказал от каждого по
possible, to everyone according to their needs, what is this,
возможности Каждому по потребности что
this is conditional, that’s right I  I
это это это условно вот правильно Я же
’m saying that everyone has a need for
говорю У каждого есть потребность в
butter, not only butter, not only that’s
масле не только в масле не только вот
right, there’s also red caviar, you want
именно есть ещё красненькую икру хочется
all sorts of delicious things, yes, that is, if
всякой вкусности да то есть если у
everyone has a need for butter, yes, it
каждого есть потребность в масле да то
turns out as a result of communism,
получается в результате коммунизма масло
everyone should have butter, not only butter,
должно было быть у всех не только масло
not only  Yes, but everyone had to have butter.
не только Да но вот масло должно было
Yes, and what? Yes, and butter Why, in countries
Да и что Да а масло Почему в странах
that did not build communism, there was butter,
которые не строили коммунизм масло было
but in countries that built communism,
а в странах которые строили коммунизм
two packs of butter were given out in the
масло две пачки в руки выдавали в
store and because they had not built it yet,
магазине и потому что они его ещё не
and that is, they  I understood, that is, they
а то есть они го во понял то есть они
said so People, they now live with
говорили так Народ они сейчас живут с
butter And you Live without butter, but through
маслом А вы Живите без масла но чере
your grandchildren they will probably have butter
ваши внуки возможно будут иметь масло да
Yes, do you really understand? Told
Да неужели ты понял Рассказывал
Told the question now: Why did
Рассказывал вопрос теперь А почему же
other countries have butter
другие страны имели масло
and those who built communism had butter?
а те кто строили коммунизм масло имели
only in the dreams of
только в мечтах
grandchildren, these are the countries that
внуков вот те которые страны которые
had
имели
butter to be able to eat This butter is
масло иметь возможность кушать Это масло
not available to all the inhabitants of this
имеют не все жители этой
country, but in the Soviet Union they could buy
страны а в Советском Союзе могли купить
butter.
масло
I heard you correctly that for example
Все я правильно Вас услышал что например
in France not everyone could buy butter,
во Франции не каждый мог купить маслом
everyone could buy butter but in line
каждый мог купить масло но в очереди
for some reason, two packs in
почему-то две пачки в
hand, yes,
руки да
but where did you get the information that
а а откуда у вас информация что во
not everyone could buy
Франции не каждый мог купить
butter in France? Well, you know, not from the BBC TV channel. But
масло Ну знаешь не с телеканала BBC А
from where. What
откуда Вот мне
interests me from there is that there is
интересно оттуда то что там есть там
capitalism there. Yes, but I have never seen, I have not
капитализм Да но я никогда не видел я не
seen photographs.  queues for butter in
видел фотографии очередей за маслом во
France A Note t
Франции А Прим т
Well, because that’s when everyone doesn’t have enough of it.
Ну потому что вот когда его не хватает
Don’t confuse Red and Square,
всем Да не путай Красное и Квадратное не
don’t s and soft. Yes, don’t confuse it,
надо з и мягкое Да не надо путать то ещё
look again. I saw it with my own
раз смотри Я видел своими личными
eyes, I stood in these queues for
глазами я стоял в этих очередях за
butter because  There wasn’t enough butter. So they
маслом потому что масла не хватало Вот
brought it in and gave it out, there
его завезли и выдавали живая очередь
was such a long line to the store and my mother took
была такая до магазина и мама брала там
two of us there because you can take six packs
двух нас потому что можно да шесть пачек
and put them in the refrigerator because
взять и Положить в холодильник потому
for 200 people they produced 100
что на На 200 человек произвели 100
packs of butter,
пачек масла
so in Russia and in France, so out of 200
так в России и во Франции так из 200
people in France in France, out of 200
человек у Франции во Франции из из 200
people can afford oil
человек масло могут себе позволить по
Money wise, only 100 people
деньгам По деньгам только 100 человек
Yeah, but in Russia, out of 200 people, everyone can
Ага а в России из 200 человек все могут
afford to buy oil, but in Russia there is
позволить себе купить масло но в России
only oil 100 oil was not enough I understood yes, I
всего масло 100 масла мало было понял да
understood everything absolutely correctly, that is  as
совершенно верно всё понял то есть как
a first-grader, as a first-grader, I
первокласснику как первокласснику я
understood that that is, half of them lived in France,
понял то есть во Франции жили э половина
they couldn’t physically buy butter Yes,
они не могли физически купить масло Да
financially, well, physically,
финансово финансово Ну да физически не
they couldn’t. Finances weren’t a matchmaker. And we
могли у них Финансов не свата А у нас
had enough money for butter, but there wasn’t
денег на масло хватало но масла не
enough butter for everyone, and damn it  you are
хватало на всех точно а блин вот это вы
beautiful, damn, an economist from God, I really
Красава блин экономист от Бога реально Я
admire your You know me, you
восхищаюсь ваший Вы меня знаете
have advanced me to a new level of knowledge of
продвинули на новый уровень познания
economic theory, it’s just cool,
экономической теории это просто классно
but what
да а с автомобилем
about cars, what about cars? Well, with cars,
а что с автомобилями Ну с автомобилями
how much could you buy a car in the Soviet Union
насколько в Советском Союзе можно было
in
купить автомобиль и во
France? Well, I’m talking about cars  I won’t
Франции Ну про автомобили я вам не
help, I’m not strong, the
помогу я не силён единственно могу
only thing I can say is
сказать единственное что я могу сказать
that in the Soviet Union a car
что в Советском Союзе автомобиль
was considered a luxury, but in France, perhaps
считался роскошью А во Франции Возможно
there is a means of transportation, and since
там средством передвижения и поскольку у
our country was involved in an
нас страна участвовала в гонке
arms race, it was not the
вооружений не
priority of human luxury, but the
Приори человеческой роскоши А в
minimum human need and
минимальной человеческой потребности и в
other values ​​again  - after all, Space
других ценностях опять-таки Космос
atom feeding all these all these on
атом кормление вот этих всех там этих на
Khlebnikov all these I understood I
Хлебников всех этих понял я я правильно
heard you correctly yes that in Russia in the Soviet
услышал вас да что в России в Советском
Union a car was a luxury and in France a
Союзе автомобиль был роскош а во Франции
means of transportation, yes, that is, in
средство передвижения да то есть во
France people could afford to buy a
Франции люди могли себе позволить купить
car Well, some  part of yes, in the
автомобиль Ну какая-то часть да
Soviet Union they could afford it Well, it’s the
Советском Союзе могли позво Ну тоже
same as with oil Well, come on, you’re a fool,
самое что и с маслом Ну давай ты дурака
you said luxury luxury is about
вы сказали роскошь роскошь - это про
wealth When you can
богатство Когда вы можете финансово
afford it financially, I explain to you that in the
позволить себе я вам объясняю что
Soviet Union people had the opportunity to
Советском Союзе у людей была возможность
buy but there were few cars Well, what
купить но автомобилей было мало Ну что
is
такое
luxury  luxury is a thing not the first
роскош роскош это вещь не первая
necessity for example This is what
необходимость шное например Это то что
Rich is Yes expensive Now let’s
Богатое такое Да дорогое Вот давайте
take it straight out luxury
сейчас прямо возьму роскош
meaning the meaning of the word
значения значение слова
so here is the wiki dictionary
так так вот вики словарь
luxury so root luxury external
роскошь так корень роскошь внешнее
splendor wealth splendor decoration
великолепие богатство пышность убранство
That is, it turns out this implies
Вот то есть получается это подразумевает
those adjectives Yes this
вот те прилагательны Да это
implies  the fact that
подразумевает то что
this is not an essential thing, but that it is
это не первая необходимости вещь а что
a thing that a person allows himself
это вещь которую человек себе позволяет
with an
при
excess of his funds, so it
избытке своих средств так вот то есть
turns out that in France people had
получается значит во Франции у людей был
an excess of funds that they could buy a
избыток средств что они могли купить
car, but in the Soviet Union there was no
автомобиль А в Советском Союзе не было
excess of funds so that they could not
избытка средств чтобы они не могли
buy  car Yes, I must repeat
купить автомобиль Да я должен повторить
what I already said,
то что я уже сказал
firstly in France. Listen to me,
во-первых во Франции Послушай меня
firstly in France, not everyone bought
во-первых во Франции не все покупали
cars, firstly, yeah, secondly, in the
автомобили это во-первых угу во-вторых в
Soviet Union, the priority was not to
Советском Союзе приоритет стоял не для
give a person luxury, but
то не то чтобы Дать человеку роскошь а
there  other priorities stood there, there were
там другие приоритеты стояли там стояли
priorities not of the person and his luxury, but of the
приоритеты не человека и его роскоши а
state, cool, that is, in short, I
государства прикольно то есть короче я я
understood. In general, let's go further,
понял В общем давайте чтобы пойти дальше
fix in France, people could buy a
зафиксируй во Франции люди могли себе
car, but they could not buy
купить автомобиль но не могли купить
oil, but in the Soviet Union, on the contrary, they
масло да А в Советском Союзе наоборот
could buy oil and a car  no no
масло могли купить а автомобиль нет нет
in France, in the same way, not everyone could
во Франции точно так же не все могли
afford a car for the money for a
позволить себе автомобиль по деньгам по
car, I believe not everyone could, yes But
автомобилю верю не все могли да Но
the number of people who could afford a
количество людей которые могли позволить
car for the money oil oil
себе по деньгам автомобиль масло масло
you understand this is not specific This is an
это понимаешь это не конкретно Это
example in general not every Frenchman could
пример в целом не каждый Француз мог
eat, roughly speaking  oysters Ponya, he
питаться грубо говоря устрицами Поня он
couldn’t eat a balanced diet The
не мог питаться сбалансированно
percentage of French people who drove
процент французов которые ездили на
private cars was much higher than the
личных автомобилях был гораздо выше чем
percentage of Soviet citizens who drove
процент советских граждан которые ездили
cars, yes, that is, a larger
на автомобилях да да то есть больший
percentage of the French could afford
процент французов мог позволить себе
cars, the number of cars in the
автомобили количество автомобилей в
Soviet Union could have been greater, I
Советском Союзе могло бы быть больше я
repeat again  there were people,
ещё раз повторяю у людей были деньги
there
автомобилей не было а Поня то есть
was money, there were no cars, but I understand, that is, there was money, there were no cars. There was money, but
деньги были автомобилей не
where do you look, there was no oil, there
а а куда же смотри масла не было
was no car, and where did the
автомобиле не было А куда же девали
money go? They are an arms race. I just
деньги они гонка вооружение Я только что
don’t have the money, so I bought it, I. A Soviet
нет деньги вот я купил я Советский
citizen earned money. But  I
гражданин заработал денег Но масло не
can’t buy oil because there is no oil, there is money,
могу купить потому что масла нету деньги
there is oil
есть масло восемьдесят первого года
born in 1981. What happened to the money in the
рождения Что произошло с деньгами в
Soviet Union You know, look again,
Советском Союзе Ты знаешь ещё раз смотри
don’t look again, I don’t know what happened,
не ещё раз я не знаю что произошло
Explain to me Why And you don’t know, you’re a
Объясните мне Почему А ты не знае ты
fool, Turn it on and don’t know what
дурачка Включаешь и не знаешь что
happened  tell me what happened to the
произошло с де раскажите Что произошло с
money, inflation ate it up In what
деньгами инфляция съела В каком
year, starting from 1989
году начиная с восемьдесят девятого Ну
Well, until 1989, let’s go
так до восемьдесят девятого давайте мы
until 1989, for example, you
до во девятого например вот она же
understand, she didn’t sit there right away,
понимаешь она же не сразу и села там
inflation there, inflation, then a collapse, then
инфляция там инфляция потом обвал потом
about And why
об А изза чего инфляция
did inflation happen?  because the money supply is
произошла потому что денежной масса
greater than the goods. Damn, that is,
больше чем товар Вот блин То есть тебе
they gave you money with which you cannot
выдавали деньги на которые ты не можешь
buy because there are no goods,
купить потому что товаров нету
really, I’m telling you this from the first minute,
правда я тебе это с первой минуты
you’re good, that is, it
рассказываю ты Молодец ты то есть
turns out, look, the poor French didn’t
получается смотри бедные французы не
have money and couldn’t do anything  buy there
имели денег и не могли что-то там купить
and rich Soviet citizens gave them
а богатые советские граждане им выдавали
a ton of money. But they couldn’t buy
море денег Но они не могли купить потому
because there was nothing to buy for that money. Yes, you
что не было что купить за эти деньги Да
know what it’s called, a planned
знаешь как это называется как плановая
economy, a super planned economy. That
экономика плановая экономика супер То
is, Let’s see where the best
есть Давайте посмотрим где жили лучши
people lived. In France or in the Soviet Union,
люди Во Франции или в Советском Союзе
relatively  what about the
относительно чего относительно вот
standard of living?
уровня жизни
the same Well, you just
в среднем это одинаково Ну это вы просто
came up with the idea that there are 100 packs of butter in France. For
придумали что 100 пачек масла во Франции
example, well, this is me for a
Я например ну это я для того для
first-grader to make it clear, not
первоклассника чтобы было понятно не не
that’s not what you came up with, you just see. That is,
это вы придумали просто видите То есть
you understand what we’re talking about, that is, there is a
ты понял о чём речь то есть там есть
Swer The rich and the poor who cannot
Свер Богатые и нищие которые не могут
go  give yourself an injection because they
пойти сделать себе укол потому что у них
don’t have money, yes, in the Soviet Union there is cabbage soup, yes
нет денег да на в Советском Союзе щи да
And in the Soviet Union,
А в Советском Союзе примерно
everything is about equalization, well, if
уравниловка все ну если вам
that’s what you want, the Soviet Union Well, once again, what’s your need for being a beggar? You’re a beggar, what do
так душу Советский Союз Ну ещ раз в чём
you have, what can you do, butter  you
тебя есть что ты можешь масло ты не
can’t buy I have free
можешь купить У меня есть бесплатное
education I have free
образование У меня есть бесплатная
medicine I have a minimum
медицина У меня есть минимальный
food package You
продуктовый набор понимаешь
understand the countries You understand The greatness of the country was and the
страны понимаешь Величие страны было а
minimum food package What
минимальный продуктовый набор Вы какого
year were you born? Well, I don’t know that
года рождения Ну я не знаю чтобы в
anyone died in the Soviet Union. What
Советском Союзе кто-то умер Вы какого
year were you born?  I’m older than you Well, what
года рождения я постарше тебя Ну какого
year of birth is that
года рождения этого достаточно какого
enough? What year of birth is that enough?
года рождения этого достаточно ну всё
Well, you see everything Yes, because look, I just
видишь Да потому что смотри Я просто
wanted to understand how much of this Union you
хотел понять сколько ты этого Союза
got,
достал
can you tell me where you are and how
можешь мне рассказать где вы и как
Mom bought you
покупала Мама тебе
clothes, I was little? Well, don’t wait
одежду я был маленький Ну как не подожди
if you  more nya I remember in the store I
если ты больше ня Я помню в магазине я
still Yes, you came to the store, how much
ещё Да вот ты приходил в магазин сколько
choice there was, I didn’t come, the store
там выбора было не приходил я магазин
brought me clothes ready, why and
мне приносили одежду готов а почему а
why couldn’t I go with you and
почему нельзя было с тобой пойти и на
try them on for you, I don’t remember, maybe I went, I don’t
померять я не помню может я и ходил я не
die  I lived in the Soviet Union for 10 years,
помри я в Советском Союзе прожил 10 лет
I remember what they bought. Yes, why did they
я помню как что покупали Да почему тебя
bring you clothes that you had already bought, but they
тебе приносили уже купленную одежду а
couldn’t take you to the store and
нельзя было повести тебя в магазин и
leave? Well, why? Well, maybe they went, maybe
поме Ну почему Ну может и ходили может и
Mary, too. Well, I wore something, I didn’t
Мери Ну в чём-то же я ходил я же не
go naked.  Exactly Yes, you
голый ходил Вот именно Да ты в чём-то
walked around in something that you managed to grab,
ходил в чём то что получилось схватить
buy and run with it because if they
купить и прибежать с ним потому что если
brought you to measure it, everything was already taken apart.
привести тебя мерить уже всё разобрали
Listen, no one died of hunger, no one
Слушай никто от голода не умирал никто
died at all, no one walked naked, no
не умирал вообще никто голым не ходил
one walked naked, I’m asking B  what did you
никто голо не ходил я спрашиваю В чём вы
wear? In what sense, what in clothes
одевались В каком смысле в чём в одежду
and what did Mom bring and you had
да то что Мама принесла а у вас было
such? What, for example, did they take for growing up? Yes it
такое Что например на вырост
was. And what happened
брали Да было было А что случалось такое
that your mother had to take clothes for
что вашей маме пришлось взять одежду на
growing up that you put on 2 years later?
вырост которую вы через 2 года одели
Listen, I don’t  I can understand why you’re
Слушай я я не могу понять зачем ты мене
asking me for time, I can’t understand how to
расспрашивает время я не могу понять как
integrate it into our topic, I’m
его встроить в нашу тему мне мне
interested, I just want to understand, here in
интересно просто я хочу понять вот во
France Yes, people bought, they came, they bought what
Франции Да люди покупали пришли купили
they needed, and here your mother had to
то что им нужно А у нас ваша мама должна
buy what you will need in a
была купить то что вам понадобится через
year  for growth Why so, well, not 2-3 years,
года на вырост Почему так ну не 2-3 года
you bent, well, by how much, well, a year, maybe a
ты загнул ну на сколько ну год может
year, even that’s why you couldn’t
быть на год даже вот почему нельзя было
buy what you needed now. Why did you
купить то что нужно сейчас Почему
buy something that will be needed in a year?
покупали то что через год Нужно
I told you because there
будет Я же тебе рассказывал потому что
was a limited quantity of goods
ограниченное количество товара было то
there wasn’t enough goods for everyone
есть на всех не хватало
Well, there was an artificial shortage e
товара Ну был искусственный дефицит е
Wait, if it’s limited It means there were
Подожди если ограниченно Значит на всех
n’t enough pants for everyone it
штанов не хватало
turns out
получается
artificially someone would walk around without
сть искусственно бы кто-то ходил без
pants it turns out If you watched
штанов получается Если ты смотрел
documentaries, they
документальные фильмы то там
said that the shortage was created
рассказывали Что дефицит создавали
artificially so that this product would be a
искусственно для того чтобы этот товар
good product
хороший товар через заднюю дверь
take it out the back door and sell it a little more expensive,
выносить а продавать чуть-чуть дороже
thereby
тем самым
enriching yourself with this. That is, look,
обогащаться вот этим То есть смотрите
let’s say there were enough goods for everyone or
давайте так товаров хватало на всех или
not enough for
не хватало на
everyone. I think that there was enough, that means there
всех Я думаю что хватало то значит не
was no shortage. It’s
было дефицита
artificial, wait, it’s artificial,
Он искусственный подожди искусственный
not a claim. But if the goods are yours,  Mom
не иску Но если товар есть ваша бы мама
bought it not not for growth But now
купила его не не на вырост А вот сейчас
And a year later I bought what I
А через год Купила то что
needed Well, maybe people had such a
нужно Ну может у людей была такая
psychology Well, like such a psychology Well,
психология Ну как такая психология Ну
why do grandmothers stock up on salt, matches and
почему бабушки запаса солью спичками и
everything else, yes, because their
всем остальным м да по потому что у них
psychology worked like that because
психология так сработала потому что
tomorrow  tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow there is a war on
завтра завтра а завтра а завтра война по
And tomorrow a war of matches is not for this the
А завтра война спичек не на это продукты
essential products And we have, that
первой необходимости А у нас есть то
is, you understand this, People
есть понимаешь это вот Люди так
have formed it this way, that is, look In general, I
сформировали то есть смотри В общем я
understand you confirmed Yes, that there
понял вы подтвердили Да что товаров не
were not enough goods Well, perhaps Yes, there was not enough, then
хватало Ну возможно Да не хватало то
look  if there weren’t enough pants for everyone,
смотри если на всех штанов не хватало то
then if there are 200 people and there are
вот если есть 200 человек а штанов
100 pants, what do the other 100 wear? I
100 в чём ходят остальные 100 Я сейс
told you, the goals don’t wear. Yes, that’s what
тебе сказал голы не ходят Да вот а в чём
they wear, the question is, and they don’t die of hunger. The
они ходят вопрос и от голода не умирают
question is, what do those who don’t have enough
вопрос А в чём ходят те кому не хватило
pants wear?
штанов
in old pants That
в старых штанах Вот то
is, we just realized that people didn’t
есть мы поняли только что Да что люди не
walk around naked because they walked around in old
ходили голыми потому что ходили в старых
pants, there were also these, as they are called, where
штанах были ещё эти как их называют где
clothes were sewn, what do you call it, an atelier, an
одежду шили как это называе ателье
atelier, yes, that is, it turns out, look People
ателье да то есть получается смотри Люди
walked for those who didn’t have enough, walked in
ходили тем кому не хватало ходили в
old ones  Well, they sewed the pants themselves. In the atelier they
старых штанах ну шили сами В ателье
turned me around in old pants,
обращали ходили в старых штанах
which they
что
wear for the rest of the year. I didn’t have this anymore. I
донашивают при мне уже такого не было Я
remember that some things I wore were my brother,
помню что некоторые вещи я носил брат
then my sister, and then they gave them to other people.
потом сестра а потом отдали ещё людям Ой
no
столько не не это сказа не выдержат не
Why children's things if you grow up quickly,
Почему детские вещи если ты рос быстро
like, well, children's things
типа ну детские вещи очень быстро
will melt out of them very quickly,
растаешь из них ва
what's wrong with them, no, no, I'm just
что это пло не не я просто я просто
saying that for some reason it turned out that way, what should I
говорю что почему-то так получалось что
buy?
э купить Извини я я буквально на пару
We
реплик понимаешь а то в котором время мы
live now, it’s called the age of
сейчас живём оно называется век
consumption, and thanks to this age of
потребления и вот благодаря этому веку
consumption, there’s already a garbage patch floating in the Pacific Ocean.
потребления в Тихом океане уже плавает
We don’t
мусорное пятно Всё мы никак не на
consume everything, we have more new ones, we
потребляем всё нам больше новае мы
make equipment that is disposable and
делаем технику которая одноразового
cannot be repaired. You
использования не подлежит ремон вы я
can make it and it has a 50-year warranty.
помз сде ут и у него гарантия 50 лет
you understand the work, but now it’s not profitable to
работы понимаешь а сейчас это невыгодно
do it, it’s not profitable, I understand,
делать невыгодно понял да А кстати А
yes, by the way, how much of the Earth’s population was there during the Soviet Union? As many souls as you can remember, about 6 billion And now there are eight,
души около 6 млрд А сейчас восем вот
eight, and population growth leads to an increase in
восемь да прирост населения даёт прирост
consumption and environmental pollution, yes,
потребления и загрязнения среды да
you know, in the Soviet Union there were
понимаешь в Советском Союзе были
paper bags  and now I understand the plastic And
бумажные пакеты а сейчас пласть понял А
here you are looking, I understand that you are, uh,
вот вы смотрите Я так понял что вы ээ
against consumption, so yes yes But you,
против потребления так да да А вот вы
like everyone else, limit your consumption, I’m
как всея ограничивайте в потреблении мне
interested in all possible ways, what do
интересно всеми возможными способами что
you eat, what do you buy as
вы едите что вы покупаете как
food, I eat
продукты я ем
And the amount of food is exactly as
А количество продуктов ровно столько
much as I need  not What kind of
сколько мне нужно не Какие Какие
products do you eat yes Most common
продукты вы едите да Самое обычные
bananas you buy
бананы покупаете
Well, lately no Because it’s
Ну последнее время нет Потому что сейчас
summer right now Well generally buys
лето сейчас своих Ну вообще покупает
bananas tangerines Yes I buy That is, you
бананы мандарины Да покупаю То есть вы
buy goods that need to be brought
покупаете товары которые нужно привезти
from another part of the world Yes pollute the ocean
из другой точки мира Да загрязнить океан
Yes burn some oil yes  that is,
Да спалить сколько-то нефти да то есть
instead of eating your
получая вместо того чтобы съесть яблочко
own apple, you consume a tangerine and
родное вы потребляете мандаринку и
a banana Yes, I understand, yes What else do you
бананчик Да понял да Что ещё вы
eat? Yes, I eat everything like an ordinary person without
едите Да ВС ем как обычный человек без
frills,
изысков
of course you don’t think that this is
едите конечно вам не кажется что это
overconsumption No why Because
сверх потребление Нет почему Потому что
in order to meat Yes because in  in my
для того чтобы мясо Да потому что в моём
city there is a poultry farm and a pig farm. Yes,
городе есть птицефабрик да свиноферма Да
how much does it pollute the environment
сколько она загрязняет окружающей среды
and what? Well, maybe you need to switch to something other than
и что Ну так может вам нужно перейти не
meat, for example, fasting city. What does a
на мясо например пость горо зам чем
pig farm pollute? You're kidding me,
загрязняет свиноферма Вы прикалываетесь
but wild animals,
а дикие животные
so look at the wild animals, wild
так вот диких животных смотрите дикие
animals in a certain territory, so
животные на определённой территории так
they are located Yes  there are none, how many on
есть они распо Да их нету сколько на
a pig farm you have thousands of heads there,
свиноферме у вас там тысячи голов
how many do you understand the difference between
сколько вы понимаете разницу между
biological waste and plastic, do you
биологическими отходами и пластиком вы
understand the difference or do you turn it on
понимаете разницу или вы опять включае
again, look at the production process of
ещё раз смотри в процессе производства
livestock farming Yes, how much
вот животноводства Да сколько
chemicals are used? What exactly and how much chemicals are
химии Что именно ка сколько химии
used in the fields in order to
используется на полях для того чтобы
grow
вырасти
for these pigs, how much chemicals are
для эти свиней сколько химии
used in the process of raising these
используется в процессе выращивания этих
pigs, uh,
свиней э
you know,
понимаете
ethical saltpeter, you know, it
этичная селитра понимаете она в океане
doesn’t float in the ocean as a plaster, but where does it
не плавает в качестве пла а куда она
go? Oh, look, meat saltpeter Yes,
куда О вот смотрите мясная селитра Да
other fertilizers get into
попадает и другие удобрения попадают в
the ground, where does it go, it doesn’t wash into the river,
землю куда оно девается оно в речку не
phosphates  And so on,
вымывается фосфаты И так дальше
you understand: I’m just floating in the ocean,
понимаете Я е раз по в океане плавает
and in the river in your city, there’s
а в речке вот в речке в вашем городе что
a lot of things that float, there’s a lot of things that
плавает много там что плавает много что
float, Yes, the result of your consumption
плавает Да результат вашего потребление
floats in this
плавает в этой
river, you know, it’s one thing when a person
речке понимаешь одно дело когда человек
reduces his consumption to a minimum, yeah,
э своё потребление сводит к минимуму угу
that’s it.  let's say Well, roughly speaking, yes, I live
вот допустим Ну грубо говоря да я живу
there in an apartment 50 KMT Well, let's assume Yes, it
там в квартире 50 КМТ Ну предположим Да
doesn't matter 50 there Yes, it seems like enough,
неважно 50 там Да вот вроде как хватает
yes, 50 M But some want 100, well, it's
да 50 М А вот некоторые хотят 100 ну
unclear why for show-off Yeah, for
непонятно для чего для понтов Угу для
there for some kind of own ego Yes, but the
там для собственного какого-то эго Да а
norm is acceptable  for a person 50 square meters
норма допустим для человека 50 квадратов
Norm And who came up with this norm, let’s say,
Норма А кто эту норму придумал допустим
that is, scientists have calculated,
то есть посчитали учёные посчитали
scientists have decided that
учёные решили что оптимально для
50 m is optimal for a person, what scientists
человека 50 м какие учёные такое
have calculated this, I tell you, for example,
посчитали я тебе к примеру говорю
you understand, well, a person understands what is
понимаешь ну человек понимает что для
optimal for him Well, you don’t understand That’s
него оптимально Ну не вот понимаешь Вот
when a person, You understand, buys
когда человек Понимаешь покупает себе
eight houses for himself, one
восемь домов
in Florida, one in California, one
одну во Флориде одну в Калифорнии одну
there in
там
Saudi Arabia in the United Arab Emirates and one
Саудовской в Арабских Эмиратах да одну
there in France there in Italy and
там во Франции Там в Италии да и в этот
he
дом он
comes to this house at best Once a year
приезжает в лучшем случае Один раз в год
and the house is standing it requires maintenance of the
а Дом стоит он требует обслуживания той
same chemicals Yes, that’s all  process,
же химии Да чтобы это всё обрабатывать
clean out there again, do some kind of repairs.
вычищать там заново ремонты какие-то
That is, I gave you
делать Вот то есть я тебе привёл
the extremes. Yes, from the way a person eats
крайности Да от того как человек кушает
there, well, roughly speaking, bananas there, smokes
там ну грубо говоря бананы там курит там
tomatoes there, and when a person buys
помидоры вот и когда человек покупает
himself 25 houses for show-off,
себе 25 домов для понтов Вот вот вот это
you understand this consumption when  a
вот это потребление понимаешь когда
person creates uh he needs one house in
человек создаёт э ему нужен один дом в
other cases he can rent
остальных случаях он может снять
hotels you children How many children do you have I
гостиниц вас детей Сколько у вас детей я
don’t plan my personal life with you Well
не собираюсь свою личную жизнь с вами Ну
I mean for 50 square meters How many
имею в виду вот на 50 квадратов Сколько
of you live in an apartment of 50 square meters
у вас живёт в квартире на 50 квадратов
Three people three people  I understand,
Челове три человека три человека понял
yes, that is, it’s a one-room,
да то есть это однокомнатная
two-room
двухкомнатная
Well, I told you approximately 50 well, 60 she’s
Ну я тебе примерно сказал 50 ну 60 она
not 50 one or two about you already see not
не 50 одной или двух о уже видите уже не
50 already 60 Nuno already well, I didn’t start there you
50 уже 60 нуно уже ну я не стал там
know right there to tell you everything down to the meter
понимаешь прямо тебе там до метра всё
Well 60 squares she Well what
рассказывать Ну 60 квадратов она Ну что
But you don’t think that this is excess
А вы вот вы не думаете что это сверх
consumption, you need to move to
потребление вам нужно переехать в
an apartment of 40 square meters No, I think that
квартиру 40 квадратов Нет я считаю что
this is optimal Why do you think this
это оптимально А почему это вы считаете
Ani, some scientists should decide for you
Ани какие-то учёные за вас должны
because according to the standards 9 square meters of
решить потому что по нормам 9 квадратов
living space per person according to
жилой площади на человек по нормам
what standards  Soviet Soviet, that is, you
каким советским советски а то есть вы
bring everything to Soviet standards, then if
всё приводите к советским нормам то если
according to Soviet standards there are three of you, you
по советским нормам вас трое у вас
should have 27
должно быть 27
square meters of living space living space Well,
квадратов жилой площади жилой площади Ну
out of sixty you have living space, how many, well,
у вас из шестидесяти жилой сколько ну
somewhere around 30 30 is already more than 27 You are
где-то 30 30 уже больше 27 Вы
not in my service  was I didn’t have You
слу у меня не было у меня не было
see, there are opportunities there, yes, well,
Понимаешь там возможности вот да вот Ну
well, well, tomorrow I’ll block the fence, there’ll be a bigger
хорошо я завтра пере горож там больше
corridor there. No no, you should
коридор сделаю Нет нет вы должны
move to a smaller
переехать в меньшую
apartment. Well, let’s not. No, I just don’t
квартиру Ну давай не Не ну просто я не
understand, you’re performing like this, and you yourself,
понимаю вы вот так выступаете а сами
so that’s all. Well, you live in  surplus
чтоб все Ну сами живёте в излишка
living space That is, you need some
жилплощади То есть Вам нужно какого-то
migrant to take 3 KMT in an apartment is
мигранта взять себе 3 КМТ в квартире
superfluous, this is not not a superfluous apartment, I understand It’s not
лишне это не не лишняя квартира понял Не
superfluous, I understand, yes, it’s super, but someone lives,
лишняя понял да супер а кто-то живёт
let’s say, someone lives in threes Well, let’s say
допустим кто-то живёт втроём Ну допустим
for 20 k
на 20 к
That is, somewhere it’s
То есть где-то это
balanced and someone lives without
сбалансированы а кто-то живёт без
a surplus
излишка
got it Cool And what year is your phone,
понял Прикольно А телефон у вас Какого
either 1918 or Dena And
года то ли восемнадцатого то ли Дена А
why did you buy a new
почему так в девятнадцатом купили новый
phone in 1919? And I didn’t have a touch phone, I
телефончик А у меня сенсорного не было я
decided to drink a sensor Well, why
решил сенсор пить Ну а почему вот вы
did you buy some Well?  you bought a new
купили какой-то Ну вы новый купили да
phone, well, yes, why didn’t you buy
телефон Ну да А почему не купили
some old push-button one? For example,
какой-то старый кнопочный Например у
I have it, why did they take a sip of it, well,
меня есть у меня зачем это отпили это ну
all my phones are working, from the very
у меня все мои телефоны рабочие с самого
first phone they all work, how many
первого телефона все работают сколько у
phones do you have now, three three phones per
вас телефонов сейчас три три телефона на
number
один номер
Yes, no, for three numbers for three numbers.
Да нет на три номера на три номера А
Why do you need three phones for three numbers? It’s
зачем вам три телефона на три номера это
not over-consumption. No, wait
не сверх потребление нет подождите ещё
again, you have three phones per person.
раз у вас на одного человека три
Yes, and you’re telling me about
телефона Да и вы мне рассказываете про
over-consumption, what’s floating in the ocean,
сверх потребление что что там в океане
look,
плавает смотрите
mobile communications have appeared  I
появился появилась мобильная связь я
bought myself a phone, it was so simple and
приобрёл себе телефон так простой
primitive. Well, at that time
примитивный Так ну на тот на тот момент
it was not a simple primitive thing, but at that time,
это был не простой примитив на на тот
the simplest one was not at the moment of the
нет самый простой был не в момент
appearance of communication. It was a bit of a
появления связи Это было немножко
luxury. Yes, then then the
роскошь Да дальше Потом появился
Internet
интернет
mobile appeared, that is, this phone was not
мобиль то есть этот телефон был
applicable, but the Internet was  it is necessary
неприменим а интернет был необходим так
for different purposes, that is, we are buying the
для разных целей то есть мы покупаем
next
следующий телефон
night phone, but on the Internet,
ночный но интерне
who will I sell it to? Well, you are
кому кому я его продам Ну вы сейчас
using
используете
it now. Well, I have it turned on, but I
его Ну он у меня включён но я почти им
hardly use it. Well, someone might need
не пользуюсь Ну кому-то может быть нужен
it, that is. So on
был то есть Так дальше
with the second phone  there was a push-button, more
атрей второй телефон был кнопочный более
modern one with Internet access, so And
современный с доступом в интернет так А
for the Third, I’m talking to you, I understand
по Третьему я с вами разговариваю понял
that now you have those previous two
то есть теперь у вас те предыдущие два
phones, they have a SIM card, they
телефона в них сим-карта есть они
work, they call you on them, yes,
работают вам звонят на них да
if so, that is, you didn’t sell them to someone
Если да то есть вы их кому-то не продали
Not because who needs it, but because
Не потому что кому он нужен а потому что
you
они вам
need them Yes, they’re not particularly gentle Well, like a dude
нужны Да не особо нежны Ну как чувак
Look, I have one phone They are
Смотри у меня есть один телефон Они они
physically obsolete, why do you need
физически морально устарели да зачем вы
their IP you electricity you charge their
их ИС вы электроэнергии вы заряжает их
electricity you understand You understand the
электроэнергии вы понимаете Вы понимаете
difference between technical progress and
разницу между техническим прогрессом и
everyday use of a plastic
каждодневный использованием пластикового
cup with sri you charge this
стаканчика с сри вы вы заряжайте этот
phone your second and third Of course
телефон свой второй и третий Конечно
Because I use it Yes, that is,
Потому что я им пользуюсь Да вот то есть
you spend electricity on it,
вы на него тратите электроэнергию за
which will burn coal somewhere or
которой спалит где-то уголь так или
nuclear fuel yes yes, that is, it turns out
ядерное топливо да да то есть получается
yes you consume too much
да вы сверх потребляете
No, it’s a necessity, I use it. Like
Нет это необходимость я им пользуюсь Как
three phones - it’s not a necessity. I have a
три телефона - это не есть необходимость
need.  it’s
у меня необходимость разные телефоны
still
вы он так получилось но вы его всё равно
charging and so on Yes, yes, in short, you
заряжается и так дальше Да да о короче
never know, someone will remember to call the
мало ли кто-то вспомнит позвонит на
old number, it’s cool,
старый номер прикольно
but you can’t, technical progress
а нельзя такое вот технический прогресс
has come up with a phone for two SIM cards. For example, you
придумал телефон на две СИМки Например
can have an old number. I have a phone with D, which
можно старый номе У меня телефон на Д
is good. Why did you take a new phone and
хорошо А зачем вы взяли новый телефон и
under  they took him a new number, you could
под него взяли новый номер можно было
just take it from the old number
просто со старого номера
because the tariff is more suitable for me
взять потому что мне тариф более
for the number that I took, I don’t know
по тому номеру который я взя я не знаю
how it is with you. But with us, in order to have an
как у вас А у нас для того чтобы
operator in Russia, well,
у на оператора оператора в России ну
in general, there are four of them in our
вообще их четыре у нас в
region.  three sim cards of TX
регионе вот три симкарты ТХ
operators and this Internet on
операторов и вот этот интернет по
which I communicate with you here, I have the
котором я с вами общаюсь здесь у меня
coolest, I understand. Didn’t you think
самый классный понял А вы не думали
then that, for example, someone wants to have
тогда что например кто-то хочет иметь
two houses just like you have three phones, he
два дома также как у вас три телефона он
also had one house, then another
тоже один дом был потом другой
in the city, but  they left the house in the village, then they
в город но дом в селе оставили потом
moved to the capital, but they left the house in the city,
переехали в столицу но дом в городе
can it be Over consumption or
оставили можно это Овер потребление или
not? I don’t think it’s necessary. Well,
нет Я не считаю что его нужно Ну так так
just like with telephones, a person had a house, and
же как с телефонами у человека был дом е
once it’s not comparable SV Why is it
раз это несопоставимо СВ Почему
not comparable, look, he was, he didn’t
несопоставимо смотрите он был он не
just buy  their greed is dumb I
просто купил ихи жадность нем Я тебе
explain to you Because there is a concept: you go to the
объясняю Потому что есть понятие ты иь в
IZH store and buy a package, you understand
магазин ИЖ покупаешь пакет понимаешь
Although you can initially take it with
Хотя ты можешь изначально взять его с
you from the previous package and there is a concept
собой прошлый пакет и есть понятие того
that there is technical progress,
что идёт технический прогресс
technical progress, yes, you have
технический прогресс да у вас с
technical progress with your phone, I understand
телефоном технический прогресс Я понял
it does not use  also technical
это не употребляет также технический
progress Yes, houses were built in the city Yes, a
прогресс Да построили дома в городе Да
man moved from the village to the city but did
человек Переехал из села в город но
not sell the rural house, left behind Yes, he
сельский домик не продал оставил Да он
lived lived in Chelyabinsk then
пожил пожил в Челябинске потом
technical progress built Moscow
технический прогресс построил Москва
City, he moved bought a house in Moscow City
Сити он переехал купил дом в Москва Сити
but the house in Chelyabinsk left him a house in the
но дом в Челябинске оставил у него дом в
village  in Chelyabinsk and Moscow is it over-
селе в Челябинске и в Москве это сверх
consumption or
потребление или
not Yes, but with telephones there is no how is this
нет Да а с телефонами нет чем это
different from telephones I told you
отличается от телефонов Я же тебе сказал
not not comparable than not comparable well
Не не сопоставимые чем не сопоставимы ну
and then he just had technical
и то у него было просто технический
progress gave him something new he needs a new
прогресс дал ему новое ему нужен новый
house for that for that  to produce a
дом для того для того чтобы произвести
telephone yes Well let's say we need 100 kW of
телефон да Ну допустим нам нужно 100 кВт
electricity let's say yes In order
электроэнергии допустим да Для того
to build a house We need 1 liter so it's
чтобы построить дом Нам нужен 1 л так он
already produced everything it's already produced yes
уже произведён вс он произведён уже да
So you just don't give your phone to
Вот Вы просто не отдаёте свой телефон
anyone
никому
about if this person sold
о если бы этот человек человек продал
his house in the village  then
свой дом в деревне то
someone would not build a new house, but
кто-то не построил бы новый дом а
would use an old house, if the
воспользовался бы старым домом если бы
same person sold his old
этот же человек продал свой старенький
phone, then someone would not buy some
телефон то кто-то бы не покупал какой-то
brand new phone, but would buy
новенький телефон да а купил бы
an old one. Maybe he needed it and there was no
старенький Может ему нужно было а так не
one to buy from  old phone and he
у кого купить старенького телефона и он
buys a new
покупает новый ре
relay old phone I’ll explain to you it’s
ле старенький телефон Я же тебе объясняю
morally obsolete Well, it’s morally obsolete you
морально устарел Ну морально устарел вы
use it You need it Yes, that means
им пользуетесь Вам он нужен Да значит
someone else might need it,
кому-то так же Он может быть нужен
but please there are many new phones for
а пожалуйста много телефонов новых
free sale Why new ones Why
свободной продажи А зачем новых Зачем
buy a new one If  you can buy
новый покупать Если можно купить
an old token for you, it’s
старенький я же тебе токон морально он
morally obsolete for you, look at it; it’s
морально устарел вам смотрите его
morally obsolete, it allows you not to
моральное устарели позволяет вам не
use it. I’m wondering what you
пользоваться Мне вот интересно что ты от
want to get out of me. I want, I want to understand,
меня хочешь добить Я хочу я хочу понять
look, why is it morally directed for you,
смотри Почему для вас он морально устрем
but you use it, it fulfills its
но вы им пользуетесь он исполняет свои
functions, that means  for some it is morally
функции значит для кого-то он морально
directed But it can also perform its
устрем Но он также может исполнять свои
functions Why should a person buy a new one
функции Зачем человеку покупать новый
if he can buy an old one and he may
если можно купить старенький а он может
want a new one Or maybe he doesn’t want it They
себе хочет новый А может он не хочет Вот
would like to buy your old one
как раз ваш старенький хотели бы купить
But you don’t sell it But I don’t  I’m selling
А вы его не продаёте А я его не продаю
because I use it, I understand, yes,
потому что я им пользуюсь понял да
good. The
хорошо
last question, do you want to return to the
Последний вопрос вы хотите вернуться в
USSR,
СССР
no, yes, Dada, come on, well done,
нет да Дада Давай
not
молодец не до
completely, damn it, just short of tin. I’m
конца блин просто короче жесть Я в
shocked by these USSR, this is something with something. Yes, in
шоке эти СССР это что-то с чем-то Да
short, the Armed Forces, there were
короче ВС
n’t enough pants for everyone  no one
хо штанов на всех не хватало никто голый
walked around naked but there’s not enough of everyone to
не ходил но шно всех не
write on th instag I don’t know
хвата пись на й instag Я не знаю для
why this is for that there to marvel at the office and
чего це то для то там дивитись на офес а
for you one or two or three clicks and you
для тебе оди два або три клика а ты
trim me and I’ll say in me there A
тримае мене и я буду казати в мене там
bunch of fouls and in me  be cool set up
Купа фолов и в мене буде класний настр
robiti but cool video write on
щоб робити но крут вдео пись на
yid
йд
taqwa Yaka
таква Яка